So it turns out that mathematics is a very powerful language.
قد تبين أن الرياضيات لغة قوية جداً.
It has generated considerable insight in physics,
ولّـدت رؤية مهمة في علم الفيزياء
in biology and economics,
وعلم الأحياء، وعلم الاقتصاد،
but not that much in the humanities and in history.
ولكنها لم تؤثر كثيراً في العلوم الإنسانية وفي التاريخ.
I think there's a belief that it's just impossible,
أظن أن ثمة إعتقاد بأنه من المستحيل
that you cannot quantify the doings of mankind,
قياس سلوك البشر كمياً،
that you cannot measure history.
وأنه لا يمكن قياس التاريخ.
But I don't think that's right.
ولكني لا أعتقد أن هذا صحيح.
I want to show you a couple of examples why.
أودّ أن أريكم بعض الأمثلة.
So my collaborator Erez and I were considering the following fact:
قمت أنا و شريكي إيريز بالنظر في القضية التالية:
that two kings separated by centuries
إنّ ملِكين تفرق بينهما قرون من الزمن
will speak a very different language.
سيتحدّثان بلغتين مختلفتين جداً.
That's a powerful historical force.
تلك قوة تاريخيّة مؤثرة.
So the king of England, Alfred the Great,
فإنّ ملك إنجلترا، ألفريد العظيم،
will use a vocabulary and grammar
سيستخدم مفردات و قواعد
that is quite different from the king of hip hop, Jay-Z.
مختلفة تماماً عمّا يستخدمه ملك الهيب هوب، جاي زي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now it's just the way it is.
هذه هي الحال
Language changes over time, and it's a powerful force.
اللغة تتغير مع الزمن، وهي قوة مؤثرة.
So Erez and I wanted to know more about that.
.أردت أنا و إيريز أن نعرف المزيد عن ذلك
So we paid attention to a particular grammatical rule, past-tense conjugation.
فركزنا اهتمامنا على قاعدة نحوية معينة؛ صيغة الفعل الماضي.
So you just add "ed" to a verb at the end to signify the past.
نضيف حرفي "إي" و "دي" إلى نهاية الفعل للدلالة على الماضي.
"Today I walk. Yesterday I walked."
"اليوم أسير. البارحة سرت".
But some verbs are irregular.
ولكن بعض الأفعال شاذة.
"Yesterday I thought."
مثلا: "بالأمس اعتقدت"
Now what's interesting about that
ما هو مثير للاهتمام هنا
is irregular verbs between Alfred and Jay-Z have become more regular.
.هو أنّ الأفعال الشاذة قد أصبحت أكثر انتظاما بين ألفريد وجاي زي
Like the verb "to wed" that you see here has become regular.
مثل فعل "أن يتزوج" الذي صار نظامياً.
So Erez and I followed the fate of over 100 irregular verbs
فقمت أنا و إيريز بتتبع أكثر من 100 فعل شاذ
through 12 centuries of English language,
عبر 12 قرن من اللغة الإنجليزية،
and we saw that there's actually a very simple mathematical pattern
فوجدنا نمطاً رياضياً بسيطاً جداً
that captures this complex historical change,
يعبر عن هذا التغير التاريخي المعقد،
namely, if a verb is 100 times more frequent than another,
إن كان أحد الأفعال يتكرر 100 مرة أكثر من الآخر
it regularizes 10 times slower.
.فإنه ينتظم أبطأ بـ10 مرات
That's a piece of history, but it comes in a mathematical wrapping.
.إنها قطعة من التاريخ، لكنها تأتي مغلفة بالرياضيات.
Now in some cases math can even help explain,
في بعض الحالات، تستطيع الرياضيات أن تساعد في تفسير
or propose explanations for, historical forces.
أو اقتراح تفسيرات للقوى التاريخية.
So here Steve Pinker and I
أنا و ستيف بينكر
were considering the magnitude of wars during the last two centuries.
كنا ندرس حجم الحروب خلال القرنين الماضيين.
There's actually a well-known regularity to them
وهناك في الواقع انتظاما معروفا لها،
where the number of wars that are 100 times deadlier
حيث أنّ الحروب التي هي 100 مرة أكثر فتكاً
is 10 times smaller.
عددها أقل بعشر مرات.
So there are 30 wars that are about as deadly as the Six Days War,
فهناك 30 حرباً بمقدار فتك "حرب الأيام الستة"،
but there's only four wars that are 100 times deadlier --
لكن أربع حروب فقط هي أكثر فتكاً ب100 مرة
like World War I.
مثل الحرب العالمية الأولى.
So what kind of historical mechanism can produce that?
فما نوع الآليات التاريخية التي تسبب ذلك؟
What's the origin of this?
ما هو مصدر ذلك؟
So Steve and I, through mathematical analysis,
قمنا أنا و ستيف من خلال التحليل الرياضي،
propose that there's actually a very simple phenomenon at the root of this,
باقتراح وجود ظاهرة بسيطة لتفسير ذلك،
which lies in our brains.
و التي تكمن في عقولنا.
This is a very well-known feature
إنها ميزة معروفة جداً
in which we perceive quantities in relative ways --
التي تمكننا من النظر نحو الكميات بطرق نسبية.
quantities like the intensity of light or the loudness of a sound.
كميات مثل شدة الضوء أو ارتفاع الصوت.
For instance, committing 10,000 soldiers to the next battle sounds like a lot.
مثلاً، إرسال 10 آلاف جندي إلى المعركة القادمة يبدو كثيراً.
It's relatively enormous if you've already committed 1,000 soldiers previously.
عدد ضخم نسبيا إن كنت قد أرسلت 1,000 جنديا مسبقاً.
But it doesn't sound so much,
ولكنه لا يبدو كبيراً جداَ،
it's not relatively enough, it won't make a difference
إنه ليس كافياً نسبياً، ولن يشكل فرقاً
if you've already committed 100,000 soldiers previously.
إن كنت قد أرسلت قبلها 100,000 جندي.
So you see that because of the way we perceive quantities,
نجد أنه بسبب الطريقة التي ننظر بها الكميات،
as the war drags on,
كلما استمرت الحرب،
the number of soldiers committed to it and the casualties
كلما كان عدد الجنود المرسلين و الضحايا
will increase not linearly --
يزداد ولكن ليس بصورة خطية
like 10,000, 11,000, 12,000 --
مثل: 10,000، 11,000، 12,000
but exponentially -- 10,000, later 20,000, later 40,000.
وإنما أسّيّا: 10,000، 20,000 ، 40,000 .
And so that explains this pattern that we've seen before.
هذا يفسر النمط الذي رأيناه سابقاً.
So here mathematics is able to link a well-known feature of the individual mind
استطاعت الرياضيات أن تربط سمة معروفة لعقل الفرد
with a long-term historical pattern
مع نمط تاريخي طويل الامتداد
that unfolds over centuries and across continents.
تشكل على مر القرون وعلى امتداد القارات.
So these types of examples, today there are just a few of them,
هناك القليل من هذه الأمثلة اليوم،
but I think in the next decade they will become commonplace.
لكنها ستصبح مألوفة خلال العقد القادم كما أظن.
The reason for that is that the historical record
والسبب في ذلك هو أن السجل التاريخي
is becoming digitized at a very fast pace.
يتم تحويله رقمياً بسرعة كبيرة.
So there's about 130 million books
فهناك حوالي 130 مليون كتاب
that have been written since the dawn of time.
كتبت منذ فجر الزمان.
Companies like Google have digitized many of them --
شركات مثل غوغل قد حولت الكثير منها إلى كتب رقمية؛
above 20 million actually.
أكثر من 20 مليون كتابا.
And when the stuff of history is available in digital form,
وعندما تتوفر مواد التاريخ بشكل رقمي،
it makes it possible for a mathematical analysis
يصبح من الممكن للتحليل الرياضي
to very quickly and very conveniently
بسرعة و بفاعلية
review trends in our history and our culture.
.باستعراض الاتجاهات في تاريخنا وحضارتنا
So I think in the next decade,
فأعتقد أنه في العقد القادم،
the sciences and the humanities will come closer together
ستتقارب العلوم البحتة بالعلوم الإنسانية أكثر
to be able to answer deep questions about mankind.
لتصبح قادرة على الإجابة عن أسئلة عميقة عن البشر.
And I think that mathematics will be a very powerful language to do that.
وأعتقد أن الرياضيات ستكون لغة قوية جداً للقيام بذلك.
It will be able to reveal new trends in our history,
سوف تكون قادرة على اكتشاف تيارات جديدة في تاريخنا،
sometimes to explain them,
وأحيانا على تفسيرها،
and maybe even in the future to predict what's going to happen.
وربما حتى على التنبؤ بما قد يحدث.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلاً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)